בוקר טוב. Boker tov.
Today's דף daf is קמ Kuf-Mem 140. We pick up at the
bottom of קלט עמוד ב. Kuf-Lamed-Tes Amud Beis. We, after a fascinating
digression about אוהל ohel and a lot of interesting אגדתא, aggadata, we
come back to talking about sifting or, a better word would be,
filtering, because focusing on liquids, on שבת. Shabbos. So the משנה Mishna
says that you cannot do
it—an earlier משנה Mishna said
you can, question about suspending the filter, putting it on the vessel,
but not to use the filter on שבת. Shabbos. This משנה Mishna
says that you can do it with a non-classic filter, with like
things like cloth or a wicker basket, so it's not a standard
vessel. So
and the גמרא Gemara first, by the way, clarified that it said
that if it's a type of
wine—I mean let's read it again actually from the גמרא, Gemara, it's
such an important הלכה, halacha, even though we read it yesterday I
want to repeat it. So קלט עמוד ב, Kuf-Lamed-Tes Amud Beis, the
last narrow line: אמר זעירי נוסן אדם יין צלול ומים צלולים לתוך
משמרת בשבת ואינו חושש. Amar Zeiri: nosen adam yayin tzalul umayim tzalulim
litoch mishmeres be-Shabbos ve-eino choshesh. You can actually put clear wine and
clear water into a filter on שבת Shabbos and you don't have
to worry. Presumably the explanation given is because people would drink it
regardless. לעכורין לא, Le-achurin lo, but cloudy, no, because that's not the
type of thing that normal people drink. מתיבי רבן שמעון בן גמליאל
אומר טורף אדם חביתו של יין יינו ושמריו ונותן לתוך משמרת בשבת
ואינו חושש, Mesei Rabban Shimon Ben Gamliel omer: toref adam chaviso shel
yayin, yeino ushmarav, venosen litoch mishmeres be-Shabbos ve-eino choshesh, that you can
even mix up the wine with its lees and then pour it
into a filter on שבת Shabbos and you don't have to worry
even though it's cloudy when you do that. So the גמרא Gemara
says: תרגמה זעירי בין הגתות שנו. Targama Zeiri: bein hagitot shanu. That's
a period between the various pressings in the vats where people would
drink it in that way. So the key though here is that
if the wine is clear and the water is clear, you can
not only can you filter it, but as opposed to our משנה
Mishna that spoke about using like a wicker basket or a cloth,
he says you could use a מסננת, misnenes, you could use a
classic filter. And this actually becomes the הלכה. halacha. The רמב"ם Rambam
actually disagrees, but the הלכה halacha paskened in the שולחן ערוך Shulchan
Aruch is that if the wine—if the wine or the water is—now
you could have just wanted to say specifically it means clear, but
if visibly there's nothing problematic about it. So, you know, maybe you
could run your water through your sink filter because if you look
at it you can't see anything, but maybe other types of things
you couldn't do like, I don't know, like pulp in a drink
or something. But the הלכה halacha gets more abstracted than just the
הלכה halacha of clear—than just the point of being clear—and it becomes
abstracted to the point that any liquid that would—most people would drink
in its current state, and you would drink in its current state,
you can use a classic filter for it on שבת, Shabbos, which
is quite a surprising and fascinating הלכה halacha that that's not considered
בורר. borer. Again, from the statement you might have just said only
if it's clear, only if it looks totally, you know, unadulterated and
what you're doing is more or less something at the invisible level.
But we actually don't rule that way; we rule that if you
would drink it and most people would drink it, you can use
even a classic filter. The requirement to use a cloth or like
a wicker basket—some non-classic filter—is if—is if people
would
be—would—like—a minority of people would drink it, but most people would preferably
not drink it this way. So once it's in the category where
most people ideally would not drink it this way, that's when you
have to use some different type of a filter. That's basically the
way the הלכה halacha is, yes.
Two questions: if you would drink it that way? Yes. Okay, and
the other is: what about for a baby? Doesn't really have a
personal preference or you want to
filter.
I guess somehow most people give it to their kids or whatever
you would probably go by that. All right, so that's very important
to know in terms of those הלכות halachos so people that need
to filter their water because of concerns of bugs or whatever have
to do it from before שבת. Shabbos. Okay, so now the גמרא
Gemara continues: מסננין היין בסודרין. misannen hayayin bisudarin.
So here's where you actually use a cloth and again this is
explained that this is talking about a case where it is somewhat
cloudy. אמר רב שימי בר חייא ובלבד שלא יעשה גומא. Amar Rav
Shimi bar Chiya: uvildad shelo yaaseh gumma. You should not make like
a indentation in the cloth because that's more like making a type
of a vessel. Again, all these concerns around putting filters on vessels
or cloths on vessels is like making a vessel. It's hard to
understand why this is seen as such an issue, but anyway that's
the way the גמרא Gemara explains it. רש"י Rashi says—another explanation in
addition to like making a vessel, עובדא דחול, uvda d'chol, is that
it'll come to collect the wine heavily in the cloth and then
you'll come to squeeze out the cloth. Okay, ובכפיפה מצרית, u-vekfifah mitrit,
or you could use a wicker basket as a type of a
filter. אמר רב חייא בר אשי אמר רב ובלבד שלא יגביה מקרקעיתו
של כלי טפח. Amar Rav Chiya bar Ashi amar Rav: uvildad shelo
yagbia mikarkito shel kli tefach. It should not be a טפח—the tefach
bottom of the wicker basket off of the bottom of the vessel
because again that's like making an אוהל. ohel. Again, pretty funny given
that the גמרא Gemara before was very skeptical of the idea that
putting something on top of a vessel is like making an אוהל,
ohel, here it seems to again be re-igniting that concern because of
the emphasis of like a טפח. tefach. So the idea of being
a טפח tefach off of a bottom is becoming like a roof
to—making it like a roof in an אוהל. ohel. אמר רב האי
פרומכא אפלגא דכובא שרי. Amar Rav: hai perumka apalgei de-kubba shari.
Putting a type of like a cover or cloth on a—this is
a like a... a piece of cloth that you would put on
on a barrel of wine to cover it. So if you put
it on half of the barrel, that's okay, you don't cover the
entire mouth of the barrel. אכולי כובא אסור. A-kulei kuba assur. On
the entire mouth of the barrel it's forbidden. Again, what's the problem?
Not clear. רש"י Rashi again says it's an issue of אהל. ohel.
Again funny because if you remember yesterday, אביי Abaye was very skeptical
that putting a cover, you know, on some vessel is making אהל,
ohel, they more try to frame it as like an עובדא דחול.
uvda d'chol. Anyway you see these types of concerns again, right? The
question about like putting again, I don't know, Tupperware which was made
for that, but like a piece of Saran Wrap that you have
out from, you know, cut from beforehand would
be a similar analogy. It's not so clear why this is seen
as so problematic.
Do you see that actually would be a problem?
I don't know. I don't know. It's hard to apply these cases
because it's very hard to understand what the principles are. אמר רב
פפא: Amar Rav Papa: לא נהדק איניש צניסא בפומא דכוזני דחביתא, Lo
nehedak inish tznisa be-pumei de-kuzni de-chavita, משום דמיחזי כמשמרת. mishum de-meichzei ki-mashmeret.
Don't put, רש"י Rashi says what this basically means is like teeth
in the mouth of a כוזני kuzni which is like a like
a vessel used to draw wine out of a barrel because it's
like a filter, it's like a sieve. So again, this would sort
of be like in those pictures where they have those teeth, you
know, in the opening to keep the ice out. So don't do
this, this is the vessel you use to draw wine out of
your wine barrel and by drawing it, it's sort of like a
slotted spoon almost is the idea. It causes the, you know, it
separates and it causes the lees to not you know get into
or not be poured out with the rest of the stuff. Again
you would have to assume you would have to assume since we're
talking about liquid, no slotted spoons usually has to do with often
slotted spoons are used like you're taking stuff out of your out
of your טשולנט, cholent, it's used to separate solids from liquids. That's,
you know, that's different. This is basically saying that it's fundamentally a
liquid and you're using to sift out a liquid. You know what
I mean? A slotted spoon is the reverse, it's like you're trying
to take out the potatoes from the טשולנט cholent and leave the
liquid behind. Here you're trying to take out the wine and leave
the other stuff behind. But you would have to say that again
that the wine would not be regularly drunk with you know you
know in its current state or else as we said before it's
not be a problem. דבי רב פפא, Debei Rav Papa, רב פפא,
Rav Papa, the house of רב פפא, Rav Papa, שפו שיכרא ממנא
למנא. shafu shichra mimana lemana. What they would do is they would
pour, you know,
beer or whatever mead from one vessel to the other and in
the process of doing that you would like leave if you pour
something slowly you can leave behind the stuff you don't want, you
know, you just tip it out slowly. So, so that's how they
would do it without using a sieve, but they would manage to
separate. Okay. Now the גמרא, Gemara, now again now presumably it's a
problem where it is a problem to use a sieve because it
is something that would not be drunk in its normal state. So
אמר ליה רב אחא מדפתי לרבינא: Amar lei Rav Acha mi-Difti le-Ravina:
so רב אחא מדפתי Rav Acha mi-Difti said to רבינא: Ravina: האי
ניצוצות, hai nitzotzot, how about the little droplets? Why are the droplets
a problem? Because if you pour something out slowly and it's got
some gook here on the bottom, for the first part of the
time you're pouring it out, you're just pouring the liquid that's above
and it's not the liquid that's actually in a mixture, right? Because
you're getting the liquid that's above the mixture as it were. But
as you keep on pouring and it gets to the point of
just tiny little drops, that's when you're separating the liquid that's mixed
into the mixture from the mixture. Okay. So he's saying even if
you're not using a vessel, you're still doing a type of a
בורר. borer. And again here we are now we do feel it's
בורר borer as opposed to before we weren't so worried about that.
So he says ניצוצות לבי רב לא חשיבי. nitzotzot le-bei Rav lo
chashivi. No, they aren't worried about that. They don't try to get
out every last drop. They only, so they do it in a
way in which they only get out the top liquid and actually
that technically is actually okay that if you can pour liquid off
of something if you do it you know so that you get
just the top liquid but once it starts getting to a slow
drip and you're really sort of you know you're separating the stuff
that's mixed in as opposed to just the stuff that's on the
top and the surface, that that becomes a problem. But here it
is considered בורר borer presumably again because it is something that is
either more visible or particularly something that it would not be drunk
in its normal state.
Yes, I'm I'm just confused. You you can leave liquid behind like
when you take out the טשולנט cholent you're leaving liquid behind but
you can't leave solid stuff behind.
No, you can leave the reason you can leave the טשולנט cholent
liquid behind is only in the case where that is a type
of a בורר, borer, you're separating the solid from the liquid, you
want the solid. So בורר borer is allowed when you satisfy three
criteria: it's אוכל מתוך פסולת, ochel mitoch psolet, you're removing the stuff
you want not the stuff you don't want, so there you're removing
the potatoes and whatever.
Not פסולת psolet necessarily what you're leaving behind, you just don't want
it at that point.
Oh, then it's not an issue at all. Then you're just taking
some and you're leaving some behind, that's not an issue at all.
If you want to leave the liquid behind.
Okay. So if you want to leave liquid behind what?
It's not necessarily something you're going to throw out.
Well the definition of פסולת psolet is stuff that you're not well
okay look so there are cases where it's not considered פסולת psolet
but פסולת psolet could also be just subjectively you don't want it.
But anyway even assuming that it is, it's allowed when you're removing
the stuff you do want, אוכל, ochel, when you're removing it to
eat to eat immediately, to eat in this immediate context so it's
right before the meal or during the meal, and when you're not
using a vessel. Now a vessel is defined as something made specifically
with the functionality of separating. It doesn't mean that you can't use
a spoon, but it is a problem to use a slotted spoon
because the function of a slotted spoon is to separate. But if
you basically scoop it up and you avoid the liquid and you
scoop the stuff you want, then that's not a problem.
So you can't use a slotted spoon?
You cannot use a slotted spoon because a slotted spoon is made
to do the act of separating. So, right.
So the opposite really, coffee press you can't use that coffee press
according to what you're saying on Shabbat.
Well, you can't use the coffee press anyway for other, the electric,
oh yeah, right.
Other kind, right, that's not electric,
right, because that's doing a בורר borer with a כלי. cli. Well,
A, no, you are pressing out the liquid, so you are doing
בורר, borer, but you're using a כלי, cli, you're using a specific
vessel for doing it. Right, exactly.
But some people do use that.
Really? A hand press on שבת? Shabbos?
They use the kind, like in Israel, they, yeah, I know people
who use it. I never understood it.
What, a French press?
You just pour, you put in the grounds and you pour the
hot
water and it goes straight through.
But it leaves the grounds.
Oh, that's okay! That's what we taught in our משנה. mishna. If
you don't do actively separate, basically that's like a tea bag. They
have coffee bags. I understand, but they have coffee bags. That's the
משנה mishna says and that's allowed because conceptually what's happening there is,
it's not like you start with a mixture of water and grounds
and now you separate. You start with grounds, you're pouring water through,
the water's picking up the flavor and continuing to go through. That's
not considered separating. That's okay. That's like a tea bag. So as
long as you heated the water before שבת, Shabbos, well, and also
the grounds is a problem. No, we should stop there because you
could be cooking the grounds. So it would have to be like
a כלי שני kli sheini or כלי שלישי kli shlishi or whatever
you need. But in terms of separating, that's what our משנה mishna
talks about pouring water through,
that's like a tea bag. No, that is okay because that's not
like normal coffee where you get it all mixed up and then
you separate and it's a תערובת. taaroves. Here it's just passing through
and picking up the flavor. That's okay because you're not in that
status and now you're separating it, you're just pouring it through and
it's picking up the flavor. That's okay. All right, yes, quickly, and
then we have to go on. Yes.
Does it have to be a filter, in other words, like a
Melitta that you have, right, like that would be right.
I don't understand what that is.
It's like a filter, but it's like plastic that goes over a
cup and you pour pre-ground.
If you're pouring liquid through and it picks up flavor and continues
on, it's okay. If you're pouring a mixture in, a mixture of
liquid with grounds and then that mixture separates, that's no good.
Right, the filter thing when you're filtering your water, right.
Okay, let's go on. תניא יעקב קרחה, Tanya Yaakov Karcha, ונותן ביצה
במסננת. venosein beitza bimesenes. Okay, so now you could put an egg
into a filter to separate out the yellow and this is going
through a filter of mustard, תניא יעקב קרחה, Tanya Yaakov Karcha, לפי
שאין עושים אותה אלא לגוון. lefi she'ein osim osah ella legavern. You
only do it for color. I have to tell you, I never
understood this הלכה. halacha. There are two ways of reading it. One
way I understand, the other way I don't. One way is that
you have your filter you used for mustard that's got a lot
of yellow color in it, and you pour your egg through it
because then it gives extra yellow color to your egg. So then
fine, no אין צביעה באוכלין ein tzviah be'ochlin or whatever, so then
fine, it's not בורר, borer, you're just doing it to pick up
the color the same way when you pour the water through the
wine, it just picks up through the grape leaves, it picks up
the flavor and it continues on, it picks up the color and
it continues on. That's easy to understand. The problem is that רש״י
Rashi here reads it a different way, which is that you actually
have the mustard below, you're pouring the egg through because you want
the yolk to go into the mustard to color the mustard. So
the question is, why isn't that בורר? borer? You're trying to extract
the yolk and not use the white, and you're using a כלי.
cli. So רש״י Rashi says, well, it's not like you don't want
the white, it's just that it's not like the white isn't food,
it's just that you want the yellow
for the color. But it's not like you're saying I want to
eat the yellow and not eat the white. Okay, but what does
that mean? Do I have to is that only allowed if I'm
going to eat the white? Am I allowed to separate two different
types of foods that are in a mixture and use one in
one way and one in the other way with כלי? cli? You
might maybe, but particularly here if you're not like immediately interested in
using the white, which nobody says you have to be, to me
it's not so clear why there should be allowed. Because we basically
do rule that there is בורר borer with different types of foods
if you want one and don't want the other. So if you
said this is particularly a case where you're also going to eat
the white, whatever, that's one thing. Anyway, I do have a very
hard time understanding this הלכה. halacha. We moving on. איתמר. Itmar. Now
we get onto other aspects of mustard. חרדל שלשו מערב שבת, Chardal
shelesho me'erev Shabbos, if you kneaded, K-N-E-A-D, if you kneaded your mustard
on ערב שבת, erev Shabbos, because mustard seed, what we call mustard,
isn't just mustard, it's like mustard seed mixed with I don't know
what like vinegar and stuff. Okay, yeah. Yeah, anyway. So and it
becomes like a paste, right? So it's like kneading, you take this
seed, this crushed seed, you mix it with some type of a
liquid, it becomes a paste. So you know, kneading is אסור assur
*assur* not just with flour. So if you kneaded it ערב שבת
erev Shabbat, *Erev Shabbat*, למחר אמר רב ממחו בכלי *le-machar Amar Rav
memacho bi-chli*. So the next day, then you can dissolve it, adding
additional liquid to continue to dissolve it in a vessel. אבל לא
ביד *Aval lo be-yad*. You can't use your hand presumably, I don't
know, to stir it with your finger or something like that.
I'm using worse בכלי *bi-chli*?
I know, that's what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* doesn't understand. I don't
even know what the problem was, but again I don't know enough
about how they used to make mustard. Anyway, אמר ליה Amar leih,
שמואל ביד אטו כל יומא ממחו ליה lei, ביד *Amar lei Shmuel
be-yad, atu kol yoma memacho lei be-yad*? What? I don't get it.
What's wrong with a hand is a problem? What, you think on
normally you use your hand? So מאכל חמורים הוא *ma'achal chamorim hu*.
To mix it with your hand or to use your hand, that's
what you would do if you would want to feed it to
your to your donkeys. I don't know what donkeys eat mustard, but
okay. אלא אמר שמואל ממחו ביד *Ela amar Shmuel memacho be-yad*. No,
no, no, you can dissolve it with your hand. That's like a
שינוי shinuy, *shinui*. ואינו ממחו בכלי *ve-eino memacho bi-chli*, not with a
vessel. Again, not clear exactly what the problem would be if you
were to use a vessel. What מלאכה *melacha* is it? You know,
it's not לש lush? *losh* by adding if it's already a mixture
and you're just loosening the mixture by adding additional liquid it's not
לש lush. *losh*, but some דרבנן d'rabanan *de-rabbanan* maybe עובדא דחול *uvda
de-chol* or something.
So if I had oatmeal which I made before and now I
want it a little bit more liquidy, I can do that?
Yes, you can, actually.
But you said not בכלי *bi-chli*.
No, that's with this mustard case. But we don't sort of generalize,
it's not exactly clear what the exact problems are, but as a
general principle of לש lush. *losh*, if you have something that's already
a mixture, adding more liquid to loosen the mixture is actually not
a problem. So again, it's not exactly clear what this was, but
maybe it was a particular type of an עובדא דחול *uvda de-chol*.
Like salad dressing, you want it to be more liquidy.
Right. איתמר *Itmar*. Well, dressing is different, that's a pure liquid. Anyway,
איתמר *Itmar*. רבי אלעזר אומר אחד זה ואחד זה אסור assur, *Rabbi
Elazar omer echad ze ve-echad ze assur*. Either way, it's אסור *assur*,
whether hand or כלי keli. *kli*. רבי יוחנן אומר אחד זה ואחד
זה מותר mutar *Rabbi Yochanan omer echad ze ve-echad ze mutar*. Either
way, it's מותר mutar *mutar*. Okay, so we were struggling what the
problem is. רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* says no problem. אביי ורבא דאמרי
תרווייהו אין הלכה כרבי יוחנן *Abaye ve-Rava de-amri tarveihu ein halacha k-Rabbi
Yochanan*. We don't rule like רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* who says it's
all מותר *mutar*. Now כאן רבי יוחנן כשיטתיה דרבי אליעזר *kan Rabbi
Yochanan k-shitateih de-Rabbi Eliezer*. Now at a later stage, רבי יוחנן *Rabbi
Yochanan* reversed his position and פסקן *pasken* like רבי אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer*
that it's all forbidden, hand or vessel. כאן רבי אליעזר כשיטתיה דשמואל
*kan Rabbi Eliezer k-shitateih de-Shmuel*. Then רבי אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer* reversed his
position, not to go over to רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* but to
go to שמואל *Shmuel* who said a hand is okay, a vessel's
no good. אביי ורבא דאמרי תרווייהו *Abaye ve-Rava de-amri tarveihu* and now
at this later stage אביי ורבא *Abaye ve-Rava* both said הלכה כרבי
יוחנן *halacha k-Rabbi Yochanan*. Now we rule like רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan*.
Now that he says everything is אסור *assur*, now we can rule
like him. Okay. אימיה דאביי *Imeih d-Abaye*. Right, exactly. אימיה דאביי *Imeih
d-Abaye*, אביי *Abaye*'s mother, again meaning his nursemaid, which we know had
all these things about remedies and so on. What?
She always says אמרה לי אם *amra li em*.
Yeah, right. עבדא ליה *avda leih* made for him this type of
a mustard, presumably on שבת Shabbat, *Shabbat*, ולא אכל *ve-lo achal*, he
refused to eat it. I guess because now it's clear he rules
like רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan*. What, how old was he when she
did this? He was already פסקנינג *paskening* at the time? I don't
know, not clear.
He was a פוסק *posek*.
I know, but אביי ורבא *Abaye ve-Rava* were consistent that said that
it was all אסור *assur*. Okay. דביתהו דזעירי *de-veiteihu de-Zeiri*, so דזעירי
*de-Zeiri*'s wife, עבדא ליה לרב חייא בר אשי *avda lei le-Rav Chiya
bar Ashi*, made this type of thing for רב חייא בר אשי
*Rav Chiya bar Ashi* presumably on שבת Shabbat, *Shabbat*, ולא אכל *ve-lo
achal*, he refused to eat it. אמרה ליה *amra leih*, she said
to him, "The רב *rav* of your רב *rav*, I do this
for your רב *rav*, for my husband דזעירי *de-Zeiri*, right, ואכל *ve-achal*,
he ate it, ואת לא אכלת *ve-at lo achalt*, then you're so
frum you don't eat it?"
Yeah. אמר רבא Amar Rava בר שבא
הוינא
קמיה דרבינא *Amar Rava bar Shaba havina kammai de-Ravina*. I was in
front of רבינא *Ravina*. ובבשו ליה בשופסא *u-vavshu leih be-shufsa* דתומא *de-tuma*,
and he basically beat it—not just before we were talking about mixing—just
like stirred it with
the clove or some inner part of a garlic. So he stirred
it, but he did it with a שינוי shinuy. *shinui*. Okay, and
this isn't an issue of לש lush. *losh*. So the issue of
לש lush, *losh* is first basically putting the liquid together with the
powder or whatever that's going to be made into a type of
a paste, and then the combination, and then it's the mixing it
together. So this becomes issues about making oatmeal on שבת Shabbat, *Shabbat*,
adding liquid to it and then mixing it, and sometimes it's allowed,
the mixing, when it's done with a שינוי shinuy *shinui*. So before
we were talking about adding liquid, it wasn't so clear what the
problem is. Here we're talking about mixing it and she says—and talking
about mixing it with a piece of garlic, which is presumably some
type of a שינוי *shinui*.
But that's only said if it's making into a paste, not like
if adding hot chocolate
to—yeah, yeah, this is all about making a paste, something that's more
like more like a—what do you call it—like a—yeah, not only substantive
but more like dough. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says... okay...
fine.
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this, אמר זוטרא לית הלכתא
ככל הני שמעתתא *Amar Zutra leit hilchata ke-chol hani shema'teta*. We don't
rule like all that discussion above, אלא כי הא דאיתמר *ela ki
ha de-itmar*, but like what's taught: חרדל chardal, שלשו מערב me'arev שבת
Shabbos. *chardal she-lasho me-erev Shabbat*, if you actually kneaded it from ערב
שבת erev Shabbat, *Erev Shabbat*, למחר ממחו בין ביד בין בכלי *le-machar
memacho bein be-yad bein bi-chli*. Oh, so we didn't understand what the
problem was? So it says yeah, you can add liquid whether with
a hand or with a vessel. So that's basically the idea of
adding additional liquid to something that's already in its paste form is
not a problem. ונותן לתוכו דבש *ve-noten le-tocho devash*, you can add
honey to it, ולא יטרוף Velo yitrof, *ve-lo itrof*, but don't beat
it because that is more of like of a לישה *lisha*, אלא
מערב Ella me'erev, *ela me-erev*, only if you did it from the
night before. And that's basically the הלכה *halacha*. Don't create the additional
paste, but if the paste is there you can add liquid, but
don't beat it except sometimes we allow that with certain שינויים. שחליים,
Shachlayim, which is, oh, what's שחליים? shachlayim? Cress, I think is how
they translate it. It doesn't help me, I don't know who cress
is.
שחליים, Shachlayim, if you grounded it from ערב שבת, erev Shabbat. obviously
can't do it on שבת, Shabbos. טוחן. tocheyn. למחר נותנים לתוכו שמן
וחומץ, Lemachar nosnim letocho shemen vechometz, you can add oil and vinegar,
וממשיך לתוכו אמיטא, umanchich letocho amita, and also draw into it אמיטא.
amita. We'll see what אמיטא amita is. ולא יטרוף, yitrof but don't
beat it.
אלא מערב, Ella me'arev, only if you did it from the night
before. שום, Shum, similarly a garlic-
It says מערב me'arev, as stir it.
I'm sorry, what did I say, beat it?
Okay, from the night before?
Oh. Oh, okay, thank you. Okay, bad, sorry. Okay, thank you very
much. אלא מערב, ella me'arev. that's how I first read it and
then I think I changed my step, but that's correct. Okay, so
לא יטרוף, lo yitrof, thank you, don't beat it, but מערב, me'arev,
you can stir it gently. Thank you. I think I misread that
before too. Thank you. Did I misread it before? I think I
did. Yeah, it was before also I said, I'm sorry, I'm sorry,
I misread that before too. It was ונותנים לתוכו דבש, venosnim letocho
d'vash, that was about the חרדל, ולא יטרוף אלא מערב, velo yitrof
ella me'arev, right. So thank you. Okay, don't know where my head
is. Anyway, so don't beat it together, but stir it gently. Fine.
So now it continues and says the following.
It says where were we? Okay, אלא מערב. ella me'arev, שום שריסקו
מערב שבת, Shum sherisko me'erev Shabbat, if you crushed a garlic from
ערב שבת, Erev Shabbat? למחר נותן לתוכו פול וגריסין, lemachar nosen letocho
pul vegrisin, the next day you can put into it, you can
put into it what are they, beans and a type of grit.
ולא ישחוק אלא מערב, Velo yischok ella me'arev, again,
but don't grind it,
אלא מערב, but mix it. See, I don't know, fine. It's an
interesting contrast. What? I know, it's an interesting contrast. Before it was
contrasting יטרוף to מערב, which is don't beat it but mix it
gently, but here לא ישחוק. lo yischok. Maybe it means don't grind
them together, meaning mix them but don't grind them together. Okay, וממשיך
אמיטא לתוכה, umanchich amita letocha, and you can put אמיטא amita into
it. מאי אמיטא? Mai amita? What's אמיטא? amita? נייניא, Naina, which is
what we call, which is mint, right? What's mint in Hebrew? נענע.
Nana. Okay. אמר אביי שמע מינה האי נייניא מעליא לתחלי, Amar Abaye
shma mina hai naina ma'alya letachli, that you see that mint is
good for cress. Now, so basically the basic point here is that
you can again, now the interesting thing is that we were allowed
to add liquid to the, to this שחליים, shachlayim, to this
ground cress. You were allowed to add שמן וחומץ, shemen vechometz, so
not all liquids are a problem.
And I'll tell you there was a great question asked of רב
משה פיינשטיין Rav Moshe Feinstein in הרב איידר Rav Eider when he
was doing his book on שבת, Shabbos so there's a whole list
of these small little questions that he asks him and where רב
משה Rav Moshe in the תשובה teshuvah answers like one-line answers. So
one question was, can you add mayonnaise to tuna fish? Is
this like adding water to flour? Is this a type of a
לש? lush Making it into a paste. And his argument to say
not is he said, as opposed, meaning not רב משה, Rav Moshe,
הרב איידר Rav Eider who was asking him, he says as opposed
to adding water to flour where basically it transforms like chemically the
flour. You don't have a powder and water, you basically have now
dough. Here basically the mayonnaise is just like a paste, right? It
doesn't change the clumps of tuna, it just holds it all together.
So it's like a glue, it's not the same.
It's also for taste.
What? It's for taste. Well no, you always, so you add stuff
for taste regardless, but you can't make it into a dough type
substance, that's לש. losh? Okay, but here he says, you might make
it and pull it together, but it's because it's like be pasted
together essentially. So I thought that was a fabulous סברא. sevara. רב
משה Rav Moshe didn't like it. רב משה Rav Moshe doesn't like
making tuna, tuna salad or egg salad on שבת, Shabbos. feels that
that's a type of a לש. Many people say it's not a
problem at all. Anyway, I raise it because the גמרא Gemara. here
talks about adding oil and vinegar to this ground cress, although you
can't add water to flour, presumably you can't add water to the
mustard, it said only if the mustard was already kneaded and made
into a paste ערב שבת. Erev Shabbat. So some things you are
allowed to add liquids if it doesn't turn it into a paste,
okay. Other things however, when the adding of liquid makes it into
a paste, that you cannot do, that's a type of a לש.
So basically the principles are: if you have the, you can add
liquids if it doesn't make it a paste, okay, and interesting question
as I said about egg salad and tuna salad. Don't add the
liquids,
I just said that. You can add liquid if it doesn't make
it a paste, don't add the liquids if it does make it
a paste. If it's already a paste you can add additional liquid
to loosen it. Don't beat it, okay, you can mix it lightly
but don't beat it, that's also a type of לש, but sometimes
the beating is the, if it's done with a שינוי, would be
allowed, okay. So very important principles of לש here in the middle
of the discussion of the mustard. All right, so now the גמרא
Gemara continues. ועושין אנומלין- Ve'osin anumleem Does it make a difference which
way you add it,
like the liquid to the solid or the
solid- Yeah, that could also be a שינוי. Within the context of
doing
a
שינוי sometimes
the order matters and so on. Okay, these are questions if making
about oatmeal. First of all, there's a question about
by always a question about בישול, bishul, כלי ראשון כלי שני, kli
rishon kli sheni, but I think most of that oatmeal stuff is
already מבושל, mevushal, right? It's the instant is, no the raw
stuff is, the raw stuff is raw but the instant is, right,
so
the
instant little oatmeal
packs are
מבושל. mevushal.
The
raw stuff is a problem.
Rav
Moshe says you can't,
many many פוסקים poskim say you can't. There's actually a great תשובה
tshuva by the ציץ אליעזר Tzitz Eliezer where he, where it's all
about, he starts talking about how there's this long long מנהג, minhag,
you know going
back whatever, so many hundreds of years whatever anyway that we make
egg salad on שבת. Shabbos Right. שבת בבוקר, Shabbos baboker, we make
egg salad on שבת. Shabbos? So he goes through the whole recipe.
I sometimes ask this to the students as a final on a
שבת Shabbos test, the whole, all the potential problems of making egg
salad. First you peel the eggs, is it בורר? borer? Then you
grind up the eggs, is that טוחן? tochen? Then you chop the
onions, is that טוחן? tochen? Then you go ahead and you add
the mayonnaise, is that לש? Okay, he goes through the whole thing,
but anyway he basically goes through the whole thing of why you're
allowed to make egg salad on שבת. Shabbos. Right. Okay. So I'm
just telling you that was what Rav Moshe said, ציץ אליעזר's Tzitz
Eliezer totally fine with it.
Okay. ועושין אנומלין בשבת, Ve'osin anomlin b'Shabbos, we gotta move. You can
make this אנומלין anomlin which is a type of a wine. תנו
רבנן, Tanu rabanan, עושין אנומלין בשבת ואין עושין אלונטית. Osin anomlin b'Shabbos
v'ein osin aluntis. Okay, but you can't do אלונטית. aluntis. ואיזו היא
אנומלין ואיזו היא אלונטית? V'eizo hi anomlin v'eizo hi aluntis? What's the
difference? אנומלין יין ודבש ופלפלין, Anomlin yayin u'dvash u'pilpelin, wine with honey
and peppers, so it's a type of a spiced wine. And therefore
it's מותר because it's just a food. The problem here is that
again, the only thing sort of bringing these issues together is food
preparation. It's not like they're combined by מה מלאכה mah melacha or
what דרבנן derabbanan? or דאורייתא d'oraisa might be, it's just like שבת
Shabbat, in the kitchen is basically could be the name of this
פרק. perek. Okay, so that's okay, you're just making food, big deal,
you're adding things together. אלונטית Aluntis is יין ישן, yayin yashan, old
wine, ומים צלולים, u'mayim tzululim, clear water, ואפרסמון, va'afarsemon, and אפרסמון afarsemon
which is what, some type of a, how did they translate that
again?
Balsam, thank you. Now why is that a problem? דעבדי לבי מסותא,
D'avdi l'bei masusa, it's made for people coming out of the bathhouse,
it's a type of medicinal thing, and we get to the medicinal
problems, the doing things that are medicinal. למקר, L'meiker, to cool off.
אמר רב יוסף, Amar Rav Yosef, they went on שבת? Shabbat. Well
no, but you can't make it on שבת Shabbat? even if nobody's
going to the bathhouse because you're making medicinal products on שבת. Shabbat,
That's the problem. It doesn't mean about going to the bathhouse, just
making this thing that's used for those purposes. אמר רב יוסף זימנא
חדא אזלי בתר מר עוקבא לבי באני. Amar Rav Yosef zimna chada
azli basar Mar Ukva l'bei bani. One time I went after Mar
Ukva to the bathhouse. כי נפיק, Ki nafik, when he came out,
אשקין כסא דחמרא, ashkiyan kasa d'chamra, and he made us drink a
cup of wine like this type of a wine. חד כסא, Chad
kasa, one cup. וחשי מבינתא דראשי ועד טופרא דכרעי. v'chashi mibinas d'rashi
v'ad tufra d'char'i. And I felt it from the right, the tips
of my hair to my toenails, דכרעי. d'char'i. Good stuff. Right. So
ואי אשקין כסא אחרינא, v'i ashkiyan kasa achrina, and if he had
made us drink a second cup, it would have had such an
impact on us, הוי מסתפינא דילמא מנכין לי מזכותא דעלמא דאתי. havi
mistafina dilma menachin li mizachusa d'alma d'asyi. I'd be afraid that it
would deduct from my merit in the world to come. So Rashi
says because it would have been so shocking to the body that
it would have risked my life so I would have needed my
merit to save me. You could say it's the opposite, it was
so good so good I had too much הנאה hana'ah in this
world. Every time my wife is like that every time we're in
Manhattan and we find a parking spot with no effort, it's like
oh there goes some עולם הבא. olam haba. So anyway.
So the גמרא Gemara. says, והא מר עוקבא דשתי כל יומא? V'ha
Mar Ukva d'shati kol yoma? But Mar Ukva drinks it every day,
so this makes it sound like it would be too much of
a shock to the system. Mar Ukva drinks it every day, how
could his system handle it? שאני מר עוקבא דדש ביה. Shani Mar
Ukva d'dash beih. No, he's accustomed to
it, so he's built up a resistance. Okay. משנה. Mishna. אין שורין
את החילתית בפושרין. Ein shorin es ha'chiltis b'poshrin. You cannot you cannot
sort of submerge חילתית, chiltis, which is I looked it up, how
do they translate? Some type of a asafoetida. Yeah, some fennel or
something.
It's kind of a fennel, it's very very potent and it sort
of is a flavor between onions and garlic. We have it in
our kitchen.
What does it do? So apparently this was something that could be
used, this was something that could be used either for a spice
or for medicinal purposes. So when, what's it called?
Asafoetida. It's kind of,
okay.
So when you, so apparently this could be used for food or
for medicinal purposes. So when you submerge it
in lukewarm water you're doing it to prepare something medicinal and that's
the problem. אבל נותן לתוך החומץ, Aval nosen l'soch hachometz, you can
add it to your vinegar, then it's for a food spice.
People are going to know, let's say you did it in cool
water or something.
Well I don't know whether people will know, but anyway we'll discuss
it in גמרא. Gemara ואין טולין את הכרשינין *V'ein tulin et hakashinim*,
you cannot now submerge the כרשינין *karshinim*, which is like what,
what is, no, how do they translate that, also some vetch? What
is... I have no idea.
Anyway, the
point is is that you would you would put this in water
to separate the the chaff from or separate the sort of impurities
from it. So this is now a problem of not medicinal preparation
but a problem of a type of a בורר *borer*, putting it
in water to separate off the
chaff. Is that not זורה *zoreh*? זורה *Zoreh*? זורה *Zoreh* is when
you use the wind and you sort of...
but to separate the chaff from...
yeah, but it doesn't matter. ולא שפין אותן *V'lo shafin otan*, and
you also can't rub it with your hand in order to remove
like the shell, אבל נותנין לתוך הכברה או לתוך הכלכלה *aval notnin
l'toch hakivra o l'toch hakalkala*, you can put it into a sieve
or a basket, meaning to carry it. And if some stuff happens
to fall out, it's not a problem. It's not exactly clear if
you're if you're hoping that that will happen or not. אין כוברין
את התבן בכברה *Ein kovrin et hateven bakivra*, you cannot also put
a, you know, the, what do you call it, straw in a
type of a sieve to remove the
chaff. ולא יתננו על גבי מקום גבוה *V'lo yitnenu al gabi makom
gavoah* בשביל שירוד המוץ *bishvil sheyeired hamotz*, that the the chaff will
sort of fall down. אבל נוטל הוא בכברה ונותן לתוך האיבוס *Aval
motel hu bakivra v'noten l'toch ha'evus*, you can use this type of
a of a of a sieve to carry it to the, you
know, sort of be like a colander to carry it to the
trough, because this would be stuff that you would feed your animals.
And if some happens to fall through the holes, that's not your
problem.
And is this not מראית עין *marit ayin* here? People think you're
using a כלי keli.
*kli* to sift? They see you carrying it to the trough, they
see you using it as a type of a basket. Okay, איבעיא
להו *Ibay'a lehu*, they ask the question, שרה מאי *shara mai*? Right?
This is the way the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* often introduces, responds to
these משניות *mishnayot* in these פרקים *perakim*. It says don't do, don't
do, don't do, how big of a problem is it? Is it
rabbinic, biblical, what's the story? So תרגמא רב אדא נרשאה קמיה דרב
יוסף שרה חייב חטאת *Targema Rav Adda Narsha'ah kamey d'Rav Yosef shara
chayav chatat*, which often there's a response that is ready to jump
in and say it's דאורייתא de'oraita *d'oraita*. Oh, if you make, if
you put
this fennel, whatever it is, in warm water, you're חייב חטאת *chayav
chatat*. Not exactly clear why. What did you do? It wasn't cooking,
what was it? Anyway, אמר ליה Amar leih, אביי *Amar lei Abaye*,
so אביי *Abaye* who often is the one that defends that it's
not
דאורייתא *d'oraita* says, אלא מעתה שרה אומצה במיא הכי נמי דמיחייב *Ela
mei'ata shara umtza b'maya hachi nami d'michayev*? What, you think like any
food preparation, even without cooking, is חייב חטאת *chayav chatat*, even putting
something in water? It's obviously not. אלא אמר אביי מדרבנן *Ela amar
Abaye m'drabbanan*, this whole thing is rabbinic, שלא יעשה כדרך שהוא עושה
בחול *shelo ya'aseh k'derech shehu oseh b'chol*, like a phrase used before.
It looks too much like what you do in the weekday. Now
this seems to be a unique, right, what defines weekday? Anyway, this
seems to be a unique problem about if it's medicinal preparation. But
it's interesting that he gives this generic explanation. בעי מיניה ba'ei mineih
רב נתן ברבי יוחנן מרבי ינאי מהו לשרות את החילתית בצונן *Ba'ei
minei Rav Natan b'rabbi Yochanan m'Rabbi Yannai mahu lishrot et hachiltit b'tzonen*?
Can you use cold water with this, with this fennel? אמר ליה
amar leih, אסור *Amar lei assur*. He says it's forbidden. והנן תנן
אין שורין את החילתית בפושרים *v'hanan tnan ein shorin et hachiltit b'poshrim*?
But our משנה Mishna *mishnah* just says the problem is with lukewarm
water. הא בצונן מותר *Ha b'tzonen mutar*? Implying that with cold water
it's okay? אמר ליה Amar leih, *Amar lei*, he said back to
him, אם כן מה בין לי ולך *im ken mah bein li
valach*? Says, oh, so then why do you ask me for? You
also, you know, I can read the משנה Mishnah. *mishnah* as well.
You know, what's the difference between us? If you're asking me, you
want my particular opinion, so I have some insight into this. So
מתניתין יחידאה היא *matnitin yachida'ah hi*, I think the משנה Mishnah *mishnah*
is דעת יחיד *da'at yachid*, דתניא d'tanya, *d'tanya*, because we taught in
a ברייתא Braita *Baraisa*, אין שורין את החילתית לא בחמין ולא בצונן
*ein shorin et hachiltit lo b'chamin v'lo b'tzonen*, you can't use either
hot or cold water. רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi אומר בחמין אסור בצונן
מותר *Rabbi Yossi omer b'chamin assur b'tzonen mutar*, hot water it's no
good, cold water it's fine. So our משנה Mishnah *mishnah* is רבי
יוסי Rabbi Yossi *Rabbi Yossi*, and I think that we פסקן *pasken*
like וחכמים *v'Chachamim* although it's not in our משנה *mishnah*, and that
it's אסור *assur* even in cold water. Okay, so גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says, למאי עבדי *L'mai avdi*? What would you do this
water vetch, whatever,
fennel in water for? ליוקרא דליבא *L'yukra d'liba*, heaviness of the heart.
Okay, I don't know what that means, indigestion, whatever, okay, heartburn. רב
אחא בר יוסף Rav Acha bar Yosef חש ביוקרא דליבא *Rav Acha
bar Yosef chash b'yukra d'liba*, Rav Acha bar Yosef had this heaviness
of the heart. אתא ata לקמיה דמר עוקבא *Ata lekamei d'Mar Ukva*,
he came to Mar עוקבא *Ukva*. אמר ליה amar leih, זיל שתי
תלתא תקלי חילתיתא בתלתא יומי *Amar lei zil sheti tlata taklei chiltita
b'tlata yomei*, go drink three measures, three רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says coin
weights, of this חילתית *chiltit*, of this חילתית *chiltit* presumably submerged in
water, over three days. Okay, so take this medicine for three days.
אזל אישתי חמישא בשבתא ומעלי שבתא *Azal ishti chamisha b'shabta u'ma'alei shabta*,
he drank it on Thursday and Friday. לצפרא אזל שיילי במדרשא *L'tzafra
azal sha'alei b'midrasha*, Shabbos morning he came and he asked in the
בית מדרש *Beis Medrash*, or, you know, what can I do? Can
I drink it today? I was still to drink it three days,
but the third day is שבת *Shabbos*. So אמר ליה Amar leih,
תנא tanna, דבי רבי אדא ואמרי לה תנא דבי מר בר רב
אדא שותה אדם קב וקביי ואינו חושש *Amar lei tana d'bei Rabbi
Adda v'amri lah tana d'bei Mar bar Rav Adda shoteh adam kav
v'kabay v'eino choshesh*, you can drink as much as you want. The
whole problem in the משנה *mishnah* is making it. Drinking it isn't
the problem, which is quite interesting because you're not supposed to take
medicine either. But again, maybe it would be not ניכר *nikar*, sometimes
you can take medicine if it's a type of thing that also
healthy people drink or that isn't obvious. So said drink as much
as you want. אמר להו *Amar lehu*, he said to them, לשרות
לא קמיבעיא לי *lishrot lo kamiba'aya li*, I never had a question
that I could drink it. כי קמיבעיא לי לשרות *Ki kamiba'aya li
lishrot*, I want to know if I could submerge it. I didn't
prepare it yesterday, and so I want to know if I could...
and the משנה *mishnah* says you can't prepare it. So מאי, what's
the story? So אמר להו רב חייא בר אבין, Amar lehu Rav
Chiyya bar Avin, בדידי הוה עובדא, Bididi hava uvda, I had a
case just like this, ואתאי שיילתי לרב אדא בר אהבה, ve'atai shayalti
leRav Adda bar Ahava, I asked רב אדא בר אהבה. Rav Adda
bar Ahava. ולא הוה בידיה, Velo hava bideih, he didn't know the
answer. אתאי שיילתי לרב הונא, Atai shayalti leRav Huna, I asked רב
הונא, Rav Huna, ואמר הכי אמר רב, ve'amar hachi amar Rav, שורה
בצונן ומניח בחמה. shoreh betzonen umeniach bechamah. You can put it in
cold water, and this is according to our משנה allowed, and you
can put it in the sun and the sun will warm it
up. Okay, so you didn't directly put it into the hot water.
That's another trick.
כמאן דשרי, Keman desharei, like the one who says it's permissible, meaning
like רבי יוסי that we quoted in the ברייתא Baraita, that said
cold water is okay. So go like רבי יוסי and do this
trick. But now the גמרא Gemara says כמאן? keman? אפילו מאן דאסר,
Afilu man de'asar,
but even according to the one that normally says it's forbidden whether
it's cold water or hot water, here it's going to be allowed.
Why? הני מילי, Hani milei,
when is it normally forbidden? היכא דלא אשתי כלל, Heicha delo ishti
kelal, if you haven't started taking this medicine at all. אבל הכא,
Aval hacha, in this case, כיון דאשתי חמישה ומעלי שבתא, keivan de'ishti
chamsha ume'allei Shabta, since you started Thursday and Friday, אי לא שתי
בשבתא מסתכן, ei lo shati beShabta mistaken, if you don't do it
on the third day, then it's going to be a particular danger.
So even if normally we wouldn't allow it, you know, this trick
only works according to one person, the cold water and putting it
in the sun, actually here it's okay regardless because you were already
in the middle of the medicinal treatment and you can finish it.
Which is really important. So even people that are like very פרום
frum about medicine on שבת, if you're like, you know, the doctor
puts you on penicillin for ten days, you don't stop taking it
on שבת. That's how you get the virus to grow back as
resilient to the medicine, you know, to the penicillin. So resistant, thank
you. Okay, resistant. Anyway, so anyway sort of a, you know, so
that is already more or less that approach is really already here
in this גמרא. Gemara So now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
מסתמיך ואזיל רב אחא בר יוסף אכתפיה דרב נחמן בר יצחק בר
אחתיה. Mistamech ve'azil Rav Acha bar Yosef akatfeih deRav Nachman bar Yitzchak
bar achateih. רב אחא בר יוסף was being carried on the shoulders
of רב נחמן בר יצחק, Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak, his nephew, the
son of his sister. אמר ליה, he said to רב נחמן בר
יצחק, Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak, כי מטית לבי רב ספרא, ki matit
levei Rav Safra, when you come to the house of רב ספרא,
Rav Safra, עיילינה, ayelineh, bring me in there, I want to go
visit רב ספרא. Rav Safra. כי מטו, Ki matu, when he came
to that, עייליה, ayelyeih, he brought him in. ובעי מיניה, Uva'ei mineih,
he asked him: מהו לסכסוכי כיתנא בשבתא? mahu lesachsochei kitna beShabta? Can
you basically rub linen, like a linen garment on שבת? You know,
like you take the garment and you like rub it against itself,
okay, to soften it. Sometimes you would do that with harsh, with
like material that had yet to be like broken in.
לסיכוכי כיתנא קמכוונת, Lesichochei kitna kamichavent, you're just trying to soften it?
ושפיר דמי, Veshappir dami, it's fine, although you could have said maybe
it's like I don't know, תיקון tikkun or something, but the גמרא
feels if it's just coming to soften it's fine.
או דילמא לאולודי חיורא קמכוונת, O dilma le'aludei chivra kamichavent, you're trying
to make to make it whiter? ואסור, Ve'asur, and it's forbidden. It's
a type of ליבון, libbun, like a, like you know, a laundering.
אמר ליה, לסיכוכי קמכוון ושפיר דמי, lesichochei kamichaven veshappir dami, you're just
doing it to soften, it's okay. It's interesting, doesn't deal with issues
about פסיק רישא, psik reisha, ניחא ליה, nicha leih, is it a
דאורייתא concern of laundering or just דרבנן? Maybe it's only laundering defined
as laundering when it's done with you know for that purpose. In
this case, who knows. But that's what he says. You're doing it
to soften, it's okay. כי נפיק, Ki nafik, אתא אמר ליה, ata
amar leih, אתא and he came, אמר ליה, מאי בעית מיניה? mai
ba'eit mineih? So then his nephew asked him, what did you ask
him? אמר ליה, from רב יוסף, Rav Yosef, from רב ספרא, Rav
Safra, אמר ליה, בעי מיניה מהו לסכסוכי כיתנא בשבתא? mahu lesachsochei kitna
beShabta?
Can you rub this type of linen on שבת, a linen garment?
ואמר לי Ve'amar li שפיר דמי, shappir dami, he said to me
it was good. So then his nephew said, וכי בעי ליה למר
סודרא? vechi ba'ei leih lemar sudra? Why didn't you ask him not
just about a garment, but why didn't you ask him like about
a סודרא, sudra, a scarf? סודרא לא קמיבעי לי, Sudra lo kamiba'ei
li, that I didn't have to ask. Why? דבעי מיניה מרב הונא,
Deba'ei mineih meRav Huna, I already asked רב הונא Rav Huna that
question. ופשט לי, Upashat li, and he came to and he gave
me an answer. Now what answer did he give him? So, so
רש"י Rashi says,
one minute.
Yeah, okay. Anyway, so he didn't say which way he answered. Oh
yeah, if you look at the side, it says ופשט לי לאיסורא,
upashat li le'issura, and he told me that that was forbidden. So
now we have to figure out why one is forbidden and why
one is not forbidden. ותיפשוט ליה למר מהא דאסור? Vetifshot leih lemar
meha de'asur? So why didn't you learn from scarf, if scarf is
forbidden, this should be forbidden? אמר ליה, no, there's a difference. התם
מיחזי כלאולודי חיורא, Hatam mechazi ke'aludei chivra, by the scarf there it's
much more obvious that you're trying to whiten it. הכא, Hacha, here,
לא מיחזי כלאולודי חיורא, lo mechazi ke'aludei chivra, I have no idea.
But somehow it's more obvious that people are trying to soften the
garment rather than whiten it or it's not as visible the effect.
By the way, some גאונים Geonim reverse which is which, that they
say that the, you know, that
both are okay, but that it was less but that just because
the התם hatam is here. Here by the garment, I thought that
actually the סודרא sudra he said was okay and the garment I
thought would have been more of a problem because it was more
like whitening. So it's funny that התם, hatam, התם hatam means over
there, presumably it means the previous case. So whole question which is
which. Okay, אמר רב חסדא האי כיתנאיה, Amar Rav Chisda hai kitnaya,
so this if you have a garment, garment basically being
hung on a type of a rack to dry
out, משלפו לדידה מכניה שרי כניה ממנה
אסור. meshalfu ledida mikanya shari kanya
mimena assur.
If you remove it from the rack it’s permissible, the rack from
it it’s forbidden. Why? Because there’s just a problem that the rack
might be like a מוקצה. muktzah. Maybe it’s not really a rack,
it’s more just like a stick. Which is funny even though it’s
a stick functioning in a way you might have said that that
defines it as a כלי. We had those whole questions, what do
you need to define like a stick or stone as a כלי.
Okay. אמר רבא said Rava ואם כלי קיבוי הוא ve'im keli kivoi
hu if it however is a rack, meaning something that’s actually made
that way,
Rashi says right it’s used by like weavers, מותר then it really
is a vessel and can go either way.
Did you put it on ערב שבת?
Yeah you put it on ערב שבת. אמר רב חסדא Amar Rav
Chisda האי קישטא דירקא hai kishta di'yarka אי חזי למאכל בהמה שרי
לטלטולי ee chazya l'meichal behema shari letitulei if you have this type
of a vegetable,
do they say do they describe what vegetable it is there?
Just a bunch of herbs. No, just a bunch of herbs. A
bundle of herbs. Yeah alright fine. Okay. Anyway, if you have a
bundle of herbs, אי חזי למאכל בהמה שרי לטלטולי ולא אסור. ee
chazya l'meichal behema shari letitulei velo assur. If it’s fit for animal
food, then it’s not מוקצה muktzah and if it isn’t it is
forbidden. Like בשמים? besamim? No presumably not, meaning it’s a type of
thing that is not yet processed and able to be used. אמר
רב חייא בר אשי אמר רב Amar Rav Chiya bar Ashi Amar
Rav האי צייא דבישרא שרי לטלטולי. hai taya de'bisra shari letitulei. If
you have a hook that’s used for hanging meat, it’s not מוקצה
muktzah you can move it. דכוורי de'kivrei if it’s for fish, אסור
it’s forbidden. Not exactly clear why. Rashi indicates that you would eat
raw meat you wouldn’t eat raw fish. I don’t know about that.
The other way around? Yeah and some I think some say that
the fish case was more smelly and therefore it was more like
מיאוס. mius. Okay. אמר רב קטינא. Amar Rav Ketina. So these are
just like random הלכות halachot seem to be relating to not food
not even just relating to food. Anyway, אמר רב קטינא העומד באמצע
המטה כאילו עומד בכריסה של אשה. Amar Rav Ketina ha'omayd be'emtza hamitta
ke'ilu omayd bikresa shel isha. If you stand in the middle of
a bed, it’s like you’re standing on the woman’s belly, which basically
Rashi just says that it’s אסור, that it’s a problem of like
הרהורים hirhurim or something, it’s inappropriate because it’s a bed where husband
and wife are together. So the גמרא actually rejects...
Does it say stand in someone
else’s bed?
Yeah maybe right or presumably. Anyway, ולאו מילתא היא. velav milta hi.
The גמרא immediately rejects that. That’s not a problem.
ואמר רב חסדא Va'amar Rav Chisda בר בי רב bar bei Rav
דזבין ירקא dezabin yarka if a Torah student buys vegetables, so meaning
this is like good advice, the good sort of like business advice
for the Torah student. It’s not limited to a Torah student, but
that’s who he was giving this advice to.
So ליזבון אריכא lizbin aricha buy long vegetables. Why? כישא ככישא kisha
kekisha bundle is like a bundle ואורחא ממילא ve'urkha mimayla and then
you benefit by its longer. Apparently they would sell it by the
bundle, so buy the bundles, when you go to the supermarket when
they sell things by unit you look for the bigger ones right?
So if they’re selling it by a bundle you buy the longer
one. It’s like the phrase before קישטא דירקא kishta di'yarka bundle of
vegetables. Okay. ואמר רב חסדא בר בי רב דזבין קניא Va'amar Rav
Chisda bar bei Rav dezabin kanya if you’re buying sticks, twigs, you
know firewood, ליזבון אריכא lizbin aricha buy the long ones. טונא כטונא
tuna ketuna bundle of boards is a bundle. It’s all sold for
the same price. ואורחא ממילא ve'urkha mimayla so you benefit from the
greater length. Okay. ואמר רב חסדא בר בי רב דלא נפישא ליה
ריפתא Va'amar Rav Chisda bar bei Rav dela nafisha lei rifta so
the other was advice anybody could use. Now we’re talking about it’s
interesting because it’s going to reflect a reality of poverty amongst the
rabbinical students and that might be why he was giving this advice
to them because they were so poor they had to worry even
about those few pennies of difference. So now we’re going to have
a couple statements that will reflect this reality. בר בי רב דלא
נפישא ליה ריפתא bar bei Rav dela nafisha lei rifta if you
have a Torah student that does not have enough bread לא ליכול
ירקא lo leichul yarka don’t eat vegetables משום דגריר mishum degarir because
vegetables increase the appetite and it’ll just make you hungrier. So ואמר
רב חסדא Va'amar Rav Chisda Rav Chisda said, the same רב חסדא,
Rav Chisda, אנא לא בעניותי אכלי ירקא ולא בעתירותי אכלי ירקא. ana
lo be'anyusi achli yarka velo be'atirusi achli yarka. When I was poor
I didn’t eat vegetables and when I was rich I didn’t eat
vegetables. בעניותי משום דגריר be'anyusi mishum degarir when I was poor because
it would increase the appetite and I wouldn’t have enough food to
satisfy, ובעתירותי ube'atirusi and when I’m rich דאמינא de'amina because I say
היכא דאזיל ירקא ליעול בישרא וכוורי. heika de'azil yarka lei'ol bisra ve'chivrei.
Rather than filling myself with vegetables I should be eating fish and
meat. So here you go he’s a real guy right? Alright. ואמר
רב חסדא Va'amar Rav Chisda Rav Chisda said בר בי רב bar
bei Rav דלא נפישא ליה ריפתא dela nafisha lei rifta if you
don’t have enough bread
לא ליבצע ביצועי lo libtza bitzuyei you should not break bread. Now
what does this mean? So Rashi well but no you have bread
you just don’t have enough. So Rashi says where’s Rashi. רש״י Rashi
says at
least
don't do a little now. לא ליבצע ביצועי, lo livtza bitzuei, right.
רש״י Rashi says לא יאכל מעט מעט, lo yochal meat meat, don't
eat little by little, don't like take little pieces off because then
you'll never get full. Like eat a full amount at once. That's
what רש״י Rashi says.
That's interesting because we do הא לחמא עניא. Ha Lachma Anya.
I know. We do that. Every little bit. Anyway, that's how רש״י
Rashi understands it means don't like take little crumbs at a time,
you know. ואמר רב חסדא, Va'amar Rav Chisda, בר בי רב דלא
נפישא ליה ריפתא לא ליבצע. bar beirav delo nefisha lei rifta lo
livtza. He also should not break bread for others. מאי טעמא? Mai
ta'ama? דלא הוי בעין יפה. de-lo avi be-ayin yafa. Because he'll be
very stingy. So you don't want him to be the one breaking
bread for others. ואמר רב חסדא, Va'amar Rav Chisda, אנא מעיקרא לא
הוינא בצענא. ana mikara lo havah batzina. I originally did not used
to break bread עד דשדי ידי בכולי מנא, ad de-shaday yadi be-kulei
mana, until I sort of put my hand in the vessel, like
a bread basket, ואשכחתי כל צורכי, ve-ashkachatei kol tzorchi, and I found
that I had enough bread for myself. Then I would break for
others and I wouldn't be stingy. But otherwise I would be afraid
to be the one to break bread because I'd need to. It's
presumably reflecting the time where he indicated before that he used to
be poor. It's very interesting, right, a lot of these statements about
רב חסדא Rav Chisda sensitive to the plight of the rabbinic student,
presumably he maybe had to deal with this a lot in his
childhood when he was young. ואמר רב חסדא, Va'amar Rav Chisda, האי
מאן דאפשר ליה למיכל נהמא דשערי, hai man de-efshar lei lemeichal nahama
de-sa'arei, if you can eat bread of barley, ואכל דחטי, ve-achal de-chittei,
and you eat wheat bread, קעבר משום בל תשחית. ka'avar mishum bal
tashchit. You're transgressing בל תשחית bal tashchit because why do you have
to spend money on these delicacies? Again, it really sort of shows
somebody that maybe, you know, had a hard life growing up and
he said why waste money, you know, and if you're okay with
this with barley bread. I know, let us finish. Okay. ואמר רב
פפא, Va'amar Rav Pappa, and רב פפא Rav Pappa said similarly, האי
מאן דאפשר למישתי שיכרא, hai man de-efshar le-mishtei shikra, if you can
get by on beer, ושאתי חמרא, ve-shatei chamra, and you drink wine,
עבר משום בל תשחית. avar mishum bal tashchit. So you're just throwing
away your money. ולאו מילתא היא. Ve-lav milta hi. That's really not
a concern. בל תשחית דגופא עדיף. Bal tashchit de-gufa adif. It's more
of a concern of, you know, of acting wasteful towards your body.
Now sometimes the גמרא says בל תשחית דגופא עדיף bal tashchit de-gufa
adif it means like if you don't do these things it'll affect
your health or you know physically it'll injure your body. But here
it seems to be making a different statement. Since you're doing it
for the sake of, you know, not in not not wasteful, but
you're doing it to take care, you know, for the sake of,
you know, treating yourself well, so that's not a בל תשחית. bal
tashchit. It does raise interesting questions. Very hard to be עובר over
on בל תשחית. bal tashchit. בל תשחית bal tashchit is just a
wanton destruction, you know, and I think sometimes we do feel like,
oh okay, I'll spend a little extra money on myself, I'll treat
myself to something and so on. But there's a point where we
actually feel, you know, you're just it's just like wasteful. You're just
throwing away money on these unnecessary delicacies. So you know there's an
interesting question about like where you draw the line. Okay, so now
the גמרא continues. ואמר רב חסדא, Va'amar Rav Chisda, בר בי רב
דלית ליה משחא, bar beirav de-leis lei mishcha, back to רב חסדא's
Rav Chisda concern with the Torah student. If a Torah student does
not have oil, בר
בי רב bar beirav by the way also probably refers to even
a younger stage than like
תלמיד דרבנן. talmid de-rabbanan. בר בי רב bar beirav presumably means like,
you know, they're still quite young, they're ממש mamash young, like maybe
even grade age, yeah anyway, בר בי רב דלית ליה משחא, bar
beirav de-leis lei mishcha, if this Torah student doesn't have oil, but
again by the way his advice it sounds like they're a little
bit taking care of themselves. Although, you know, now we have more
of a teenage, we have more of adolescence than they had in
the old old times, you know, so people were much more expected
to be self-reliant at a younger age. Anyway, if he doesn't have
oil, נימש במייא דחרביצי, nimesh be-maya de-charbitzi, should bathe himself with water
from the ditches, because I don't know, somehow it might be oily
depending on where the ditch is, anyway and that somehow does something
similar.
Okay. ואמר רב חסדא, Va'amar Rav Chisda, בר בי רב דזבין אומצא,
bar beirav de-zavin umtza, if you're buying meat and you're buying meat
from raw meat, ליזבון אונקא, lizbin unka, you should buy it from
the neck area of the animal, דאית ביה תלתא מיני בשרא. de-it
beih tlata minei bisra. It has three different types of
meat are there, so you'll get, you know, if you finally have
some money to buy meat, this is the best place, you know,
it has fatty meat and has lean meat and so on, so
you know, since you won't be having meat so much, you know,
this is the way to buy your meat. ואמר רב חסדא, Va'amar
Rav Chisda, בר בי רב דזבין קיטוניתא, bar beirav de-zavin kitunisa, and
this ties back to our discussion before about the קיטוניתא, kitunisa, about
the linen
garment, ליזבון מן דנהר אבא, lizbin min de-Nahar Abba, they should buy
the stuff from נהר אבא, Nahar Abba, וניחווריה כל תלתין יומי, ve-nichavrei
kol tlatsin yoma, and you should, you know, you should launder it
every 30 days. It's like, you know, like take your car in
for, you know, get the oil change every, you know, what is
it, 20,000 miles or so? Anyway, so if you cause you gotta
make it last, okay? It's, you know, make a purchase, buy quality
clothing and treat it well, make it last.
Okay. What? That
long? Okay. דמפציא ליה תריסר ירחי שתא, De-mapatzeia lei tresar yarchi shata,
and then it will last all 12 months of the year. Okay.
ואנא ערבא, Va-ana areva, I will be the I will be the
guarantor. Trust me on this. Spend money, buy quality stuff, treat it
well, it'll last you well. מאי קיטוניתא? Mai kitunisa? What does the
phrase קיטוניתא kitunisa mean? Why not just כיתונת kitonet or something? קיטא
נאה, Kita na'eh, means a
a beautiful garment. Okay. ואמר רב חסדא, Va'amar Rav Chisda, בר בי
רב דלא ליתיב אציפתא חדתא, bar beirav de-lo lisei batzifsa chadta, don't
sit on a new, on a like a mat. A new mat,
reed mat, דמכליא מאניה, d'mechalyo manyei, it'll it'll destroy your clothes. Okay,
like it'll be I don't know, you know, wet, moist, no, I
think moist, and anywho. ואמר רב חסדא V'amar Rav Chisda בר בי
רב Bar bei Rav לא לושאל מאניה לאושפיזיה lo lishal manyei l'ushpizaye
ליה, do not give your clothes to your host, maybe they would
also stay in people's homes or in an inn, anyway, don't give
it to your host to do the laundry for you. דלאו אורח
ארעא, D'lav orech ara, it's not it's דרך ארץ. Derech Eretz. דילמא
חזי ביה מידי ואתי למגניה, Dilma chazi bei midi v'asi l'meganyei, maybe
you will have had some seminal emission or something, and otherwise and
it'll be inappropriate that, you know, that they should see this and
it's not כבוד Kavod to you or to them. אמר להו רב
חסדא לבנתיה, Amar lehu Rav Chisda l'vantei, now, very interesting last sort
of story about this, okay, תהויין צניען באפי גברייכו, Tehavayan tniyan b'apei
gavreichu, be be modest in the presence of your husbands.
He says before they got married?
Presumably. לא תאכלו נהמא באפי גברייכו, Lo sochlu nahama b'apei gavreichu, don't
eat bread in their presence. לא תאכלו ירקא בליליא, Lo sochlu yarka
b'leilya,
now, don't eat vegetables at night presumably that would lead to bad
breath or something, or maybe a, you know, passing gas. לא תאכלו
תמרי בליליא, Lo sochlu tamrei b'leilya, similarly don't eat dates at night,
similar concerns. ולא תשתו שיכרא בליליא, V'lo sishtu shichra b'leilya, or drink
beer, all these things I think רש"י Rashi says the vegetables is
bad breath, the the beer and the dates is because it'll they'll
be like diuretics and also lead to passing gas. Okay. ולא תפנו
היכא דמפני גברייכו, V'lo tifnu heicha d'mifnei gavreichu, and don't go to
the bathroom in the same place your husbands do, also that's just
somehow, you know, even though you're married, there's you know it doesn't
you know doesn't mean like just totally be yourself, right? You have
to respect certain privacy, act in certain ways, you know, because you
don't want, you know, you have to respect the other person and
their sensibilities and so on. Okay. וכי קא קרי אבבא אינשי, V'chi
ka kari abava inshi, when somebody knocks at your door, לא תימרון
מנו, lo teimrun manu, who's there?
אלא מני, Ella mani, who's there? Now, מנו manu and מני mani
is in the masculine and feminine. So don't say it in the
masculine which makes oh, you're expecting a male visitor? Say it in
the feminine. Okay. So, now, okay, all that was interesting. Now we
get to the real punchline. נקיט מרגניצא בחדא ידיה, Nakit marganisa b'chada
yadei, I'll give you the literal translation and then I'll tell you
what רש"י Rashi says it means. נקיט מרגניצא בחדא ידיה, Nakit marganisa
b'chada yadei, hold a or he held whatever a pearl in one
hand, וכורא בחדא ידיה, v'kura b'chada yadei, and it's like a type
of might be a like
a well רש"י Rashi says it could mean like רש"י Rashi says
it's like a like a כורא, kura, what's that a a not
an urn a furnace or something but a kiln or something right
בחדא b'chada in the other hand ידיה. yadei. מרגניצא אחוי להו, Marganisa
achvei lehu, he showed them or I'll read it first this way:
he showed them the pearl, וכורא לא אחוי להו, v'kura lo achvei
lehu, and he didn't show them the kiln or whatever else this
was, the small other thing he was holding in his hand, עד
דניצטערא, ad d'nistara, until they were pained, והדר אחוי להו, v'hadar achvei
lehu, and then he showed it them. So the way I just
read it, this is what he was showing to his daughters and
it was basically demonstrating them the value of
privacy. That actually if I show you this pearl right away, it's
no big deal. If I hide something of less value, ooh, it's
a secret, it's a present, it's all wrapped up, then you know
it's like much more exciting and you're much more interested, so there's
a even with your husband there's a value of privacy because rather
than just like just hanging it all out there. Because it makes
things more treasured and valued when they're a little bit more hidden
and they're not readily available. So even the kiln which isn't valuable,
right? Even this thing which isn't valuable, when it's hidden, you become
much more intrigued and interested and so on, and it's a value
of of maintaining certain, you know, privacy and so on and not
just like I said hang letting your hair totally loose or whatever
in front of your spouse. That's one way of reading it. רש"י
reads this that this is a metaphor and he was talking about
how to act in, you know, in bed, in sexual contact, and
says that it's referring that the first is the that the מרגניצא
marganisa are breasts and the כורא kura refers to the, you know,
to the genitals and talks about first like about foreplay, that you,
you know, first, you know, sort of, you know, engage in certain
types of of foreplay before you get to the to the heavier
stuff. So that he was really giving them some sexual advice in
the bedroom.
He says it's his
daughters, he's supposed to like, you know, having his his wife tell
them, right.
He's very close to his daughters, we know him from other stories.
He says somewhere I preferred my daughters to my sons.
Oh, yeah? Really? Interesting.
Okay. Same thing about why so young. Okay, let us just shh,
can we just read I'm just going to read to the
משנה. אין שולין בכבישנין, Ein sholin b'chvishnin, מתניתין דלא כהאי תנא, matnisin
d'lo k'hai tanna, a משנה that speaks about you can carry stuff
in a basket with like like a with a or like a
type of of a of a sieve basket that things could fall
out, if that's not your intent, that's not like the following תנא,
דתניא, it taught a ברייתא, רבי אליעזר בן יעקב אומר, Rabbi Eliezer
ben Yaakov omer, אין משגיחין בכבירה כל עיקר, ein mashgichin b'chavira kol
ikar, you cannot all use this type of a sieve basket, even
if that's not what you're doing, because it looks like and you
might intend to be actually using it to sieve. Okay, we will
pick up with the משנה tomorrow.